<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Continuum]]></title>
  <link href="http://wellsie1116.github.com/continuum/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://wellsie1116.github.com/continuum/"/>
  <updated>2011-12-01T12:18:02-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://wellsie1116.github.com/continuum/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kevin Wells]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Things Started]]></title>
    <link href="http://wellsie1116.github.com/continuum/blog/2011/11/30/getting-things-started/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-30T22:45:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://wellsie1116.github.com/continuum/blog/2011/11/30/getting-things-started</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Game Overview</h2>

<p>My tentative plan for the game is to combine elements from both
<a href="http://braid-game.com">Braid</a> and <a href="http://www.thinkwithportals.com">Portal</a>
with some new game play ideas I come up with.  My main goal with this game is
to explore how a game could bend the ideas of time and space (space-time
<strong>continuum</strong>) to create a unique and innovative game play experience.</p>

<h3>Breaking Time</h3>

<p>At its heart, Continuum will be a puzzle game where the player is presented with
a 3 dimensional world where they need to navigate to the exit.  In order to
reach their goal, they will need to utilize various abilities that they acquire
throughout the game (related to manipulating time and space).  Players will have
no time limit and will have only 1 life, but even though the game will have
elements deadly to players, they will only need 1 life because the players will
have the ability to rewind time.  Even if a player dies, they can simply rewind
time to a state where they were still alive, hopefully making better choices in
the future.  For someone that has not played games such as Braid in the past,
this concept can seem a bit odd.  Consider the following timeline:</p>

<pre><code>            :----------&gt;-------&gt;
            :     0.5     1.0
            :-------:
              -1.0  :
local  -------------:
         1.0

global ------------------------------------------------------------------&gt;
       1    3       2 4        5
</code></pre>

<p>In this graph, <em>global</em> is time as it passes for a passive observer, whereas
<em>local</em> is time as it passes for the player, where they have the ability to
control the flow of time.  In this example, the player plays from timestep 1 to
2, where the player hits an obstacle and dies.  They then rewind time back to
timestep 3, where they continue playing at half of the normal rate of time.
After crossing the difficult obstacle (at timestep 4), they continue playing
until timestep 5, where they solve the puzzle.  To someone watching the game,
the would not see the progression from timestep 2 to 3.  A passive observer
would only see the following sequences of timesteps: 1, 3, 4, 5.</p>

<p>Players will gain additional time manipulation abilities throughout the game.
Consider the following timeline:</p>

<pre><code>                    :----------X
                    :
local  -------------:              :---------X
                    :              :
                    :--------------:
                                   :
                                   :-----------------&gt;

global ------------------------------------------------------------------&gt;
       1            2          3   4         5       6
</code></pre>

<p>In this example, the player has the ability to &#8216;fork&#8217; time, the ability to
duplicate themselves and control both timelines.  How is this useful?  Consider
a simple example.  In a level, there is a door which must be opened by a switch
that it takes 5 seconds to walk to.  The switch, however, will only keep the
door open for 3 seconds.  To solve the puzzle, the player can set a marker point
(timesteps 2 and 4 in the example above), go and press the button, and then jump
back to the marker point, and simply walk through the door when their double
presses the button.</p>

<p>In the example above, the player moves through time normally from step 1 to 2,
at which point they set a fork marker.  They then move through the top branch to
step 3, where they instantaneously jump back to step 2 and then move through the
lower branch to step 4.  During this time, they could see their &#8216;double&#8217; moving
through the level doing whatever they did.  This example has a second fork in
time, and it functions the same as the first.</p>

<h3>Breaking Space</h3>

<p>Time permitting, I would like to also incorporate space manipulation elements
similar to the popular game Portal, which involves the player specifying two
arbitrary points in the level that they can instantaneously jump from one point
to the other.  I plan on basing the game in the same universe as Portal, and it
would be fun to incorporate aspects of other games in that universe.</p>

<h2>Choosing a Framework</h2>

<p>While the focus of this project is on creating a full featured game, I feel like
I will be unable to use any existing full-package frameworks to do the job
mostly because this game breaks conventional ideas about first person shooters.
Most game engines don&#8217;t support forking time, let alone introducing portals.
One game engine that I did look into was Source, the same game engine that was
used to make Portal and Portal 2.  It is possible to write mods for those games,
but, unfortunately, Valve has not yet released the SDK for Portal 2, which is my
target platform if I would make a mod to the game.  Instead, I plan on using SDL
to host the application, OpenGL for graphics rendering, OpenAL for 3D audio, ODE
for my physics engine, and a blend of C and Python for the implementation language.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
